Cool.
Hello everyone, and
welcome to CME 295--
Transformers and
Large Language Models.
So my name is Afshine.
And I will be teaching
this class with Shervine,
who's in the back.
And before I start, I'm just
going to introduce ourselves.
So we're twin brothers,
and we actually
had a similar background.
So we both went to
a school in France
called Centrale Paris, and
then we each went our way.
So on my end, I went to
MIT, and then Shervine
went to Stanford to do
the ICME Master's program.
And after that, I guess
our industry background
is very similar as well.
So I first went
to Uber, and then
Shervine came to Uber
as well, and then
Shervine left to Google,
and I went to Google.
And then very recently,
I joined Netflix,
and Shervine joined
Netflix as well.
And we've been working
on Large Language Models.
So yeah, I guess we have
technical backgrounds,
and mostly oriented
towards LLMs.
OK, so why are we
doing this class?
So since 2020, Shervine and I
have been specializing in NLP.
And we've been giving this class
in the format of a workshop that
was done on a yearly basis.
So in 2021, 2022, 2023,
2024, ChatGPT came in 2022,
and suddenly there was a
lot of interest for LLMs.
And so it's actually
last spring that we
started to offer this
class as a Stanford course
that is now called CME 295, and
this is the second instance.
Cool.
So what can you expect
from this class?
So first of all, LLMs are
basically everywhere now.
And I guess our goal
here is twofold.
So the first one is to learn
about the underlying mechanism
that makes all this work.
And we're going to see
the transformer, which
is the foundational architecture
that makes all this work.
And then the second thing is to
know how these LLMs are trained
and where they are applied.
So in case you're
still wondering
if this class is
good for you, I would
say that this class is great
for people who just in general
have an interest in this field,
either because you wanted
to make it your career goal,
if you want to be a research
scientist or an ML scientist,
or if you want to develop
a personal project that
relies on LLMs to some extent,
to just knowing the
caveats, I guess what works,
what doesn't, or just say if
you're in a separate field
and you just want to know how
this whole AI, GenAI, LLMs
thing works and how you can
apply it to your domain.
So now in terms
of prerequisites,
I would say that
at a very minimum
you should have some
foundations in ML,
like basically know how
a model is trained, what
a neural network is, and also
some basics in linear algebra,
so basically how matrices
are multiplied, for instance.
But even if you have
a developing, I guess,
competency in this
field, I guess it's fine,
we're still be here
to help you out.
But I guess this is like the
ideal set of prerequisites.
Cool.
So still on the logistics, so
this class will be held every
Friday from 3:30 to 5:20,
and it will be held here.
So this class is two units.
And you have the choice to
either take it as a letter
or a credit/non-credit.
So as you could
tell from the setup,
we're basically
recording this class.
And if you cannot for some
reason attend this time,
this slot, we'll make sure with
Shervine to make the recordings
available, either tonight,
like every Friday night,
or on Saturday.
So in terms of the
grades, so what
we're doing for this quarter
is to have two exams.
So one is the
midterm, which will
be happening during our fifth
instance, which is October 24.
And then the second exam
will be the final exam,
which will be held in
the week of December 8.
So date is still TBD.
So we'll let you know.
Cool.
So every time we
have a lecture, we'll
be posting the slides and the
recordings on the website.
And in case you're
interested, we also
have the syllabus
in there, so you
can know a little bit what
are the topics that we'll
be talking about.
And the class textbook is
this Super Study Guide--
Transformer LLMs.
So we have a copy here in
case you want to take a look.
So yeah, I guess a
lot of the concepts
that we have in this class
will actually be in the book.
So I guess it's a helpful
way to follow this as well.
And also, we did some very
short, condensed version
of this whole class that we
called the VIP cheat sheet.
So this one is
available on GitHub
in case you're interested.
And yeah, we also translated it
into a number of languages now.
By the way, if your language
is not there, let us know,
and happy to work on
that as well together.
OK, cool.
I think it's the last things
on the logistics part.
So in terms of
announcements, we'll
be posting things on Canvas.
In case you have
any questions, you
can of course reach out to us.
But there is also a tab on
Canvas that's called Ed.
I'm sure you're familiar.
So you just click on that,
just post your question,
and then Shervine and
I will be responding.
And I guess to reach out to
us, you have this mailing list.
Or we're just two,
so just ding us.
Cool.
So on the logistics, do we
have any questions so far?
And one thing I
forgot to mention
is that, given that we're
recording this class,
I guess if you're
asking a question,
it may not be super
clear for the viewer what
your question was.
So I'm going to make an effort
to just repeat your question.
It will sound weird, but I'll
try to not forget, but yeah.
So any questions so
far on the logistics?
Yeah.
So the question is whether there
are coding parts in the exams.
So the answer is no.
So the exams will
purely focus on concepts
that we see in class.
And actually, it's
not meant to trap you.
So I guess if you
follow the class, if you
see the slides and the concepts
that we see, should be fine.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Question is, if you're
waitlisted, what do you do?
I think, so by experience,
a lot of people
will finalize their schedule.
Some people will
drop, some won't.
In case you're still
waitlisted, come talk to us.
But I'm pretty
confident it's going
to be OK, because I think the
waitlist right now is six.
So, I think it should be fine.
Cool.
Yeah.
They will be on the
website, and we'll
make sure to also
post a link on Canvas.
Yeah.
So the question was,
where are the slides.
And they're on the website.
Cool, yeah.
So question is on the
weighting of the exams.
So there is no homework.
So 50% is midterm, 50% is final.
And no grades--
I mean, no weights
are from that.
And particular, I
mean if this slot
is conflicting with
something, just keep in mind
that we are recording this.
So it's fine if you cannot
attend this session.
Yeah.
Sorry?
Oh, is the question
that the final
is about just the second
half of the class?
We have not written
the exam yet,
but I think this is
something we are thinking of.
So the final is probably going
to be about the second half
of the topics.
Cool.
OK, long story short, 50%
midterm, 50% final exam.
And it's a fun class.
Cool.
So with that, I'm going to
just slowly start the class.
So another thing that
I want to mention
was every time we're
talking about something,
you will see that at
the bottom of the slide
there will be a source, and
it's mostly for-- so first,
to credits, whatever,
we're quoting, but also
for you to dig into
those materials a bit
more in case you're interested.
Because, of course, we have
only two hours per week,
and we only have
nine or 10 weeks,
so there's nowhere near enough
time for us to cover everything.
And the second disclaimer is
you will see that the field is
full of abbreviations.
So I myself was completely
scared of them when I started.
But hopefully by the
end of the class,
you will have a
mental mapping of what
these abbreviations
mean, respect
to what they correspond to.
So yes, so if you
have a mental mapping
towards the end of the class,
then we know e did a good job.
So with that, let's start.
And I guess we will start at
a very high level, because I
will just assume that I guess
we're starting from scratch.
And we're going to talk
about NLP in general.
So NLP is going to be
our first abbreviation.
So NLP stands for Natural
Language Processing.
And it is a field that is
around manipulating text,
just computing things with text.
And at a very high level, can
basically classify NLP tasks
into three buckets.
So the first bucket is what
we call classification.
So we have an input
text as an input.
And then what we want
is to predict something.
So one example is you
have a movie review
and you want to predict whether
the sentiment is positive,
negative, or neutral.
So that's one example.
You can also have intent
detection, just knowing
what, for instance,
the person wants to do.
So let's suppose you say, I want
to create an alarm for tomorrow.
So the intent here
is create an alarm.
So also to detect a
language-- so for instance,
if you write among
French, you want
to detect that text is in
French, topic modeling.
The second category is what
we call multi-classification.
So we still have
a text as input,
but this time we predict
more than one thing.
So you have a number of
tasks in that bucket as well.
So one that is very popular is
called Named Entity Recognition,
a.k.a.
NER.
So what that task does
is, given an input text,
we want to basically label
some specific words, like,
for instance, identifying
whether something
is a location, or
a time, and so on.
And then you have some
other tasks as well
that are a little bit more
on the linguistic side.
I think they're less
trendy now, but I
guess 10 years ago
it was something
that people would study a lot.
So part of speech tagging, which
is about just figuring out which
word is a noun, a
verb, et cetera,
or some parsing-related tasks,
so dependency or constituency
parsing.
And then the last bucket, which
is very popular these days is
the generation bucket.
So you have the text
as input, and you also
have text as output.
And here the length
can be variable,
meaning you don't know what
the length of your output text
will be beforehand.
So here you have several tasks.
So for instance, you
have machine translation.
So for instance,
something in English and I
wanted to let's say German.
Question answering--
so typically
the ChatGPT, Gemini that
you're using, the assistant.
So you ask a question
and you have a response.
And then you have other tasks
as well, like summarization,
you want to summarize
an article, let's say,
or just generate something.
So something can be generate
codes, generate a poem,
can also be a lot of things.
Cool.
So now what we will do is go
through these tasks one by one
to just illustrate what
people typically handle with.
So we're going to start
with the first bucket, which
is the classification bucket.
And here we're
going to illustrate
this with the sentiment
extraction task.
So let's suppose
we have a sentence,
"this teddy bear is so cute."
We want our model to predict
this to be a positive sentiment.
So typically what you
would use is sentiment
extraction data sets.
So I mentioned movie reviews,
so this is IMDb critiques.
But you also have
reviews about products,
so Amazon reviews or tweets.
Now I guess it's
called X, so X posts.
And the way you would
evaluate such outputs
would be by typically using
traditional classification
metrics.
So you have accuracy,
which is what
is the percentage
of the observations
that you correctly predicted.
But you also have
two key metrics,
which I'm just going to remind.
I'm not sure if everyone
knows about them.
So one is precision,
which is, out of all
the positive predictions
that you made,
which ones were correct?
And then the second
one is recall.
Out of all the true
labels, how many of them
did you correctly predict
as being positive?
And you have this metric
called the F1 score, which
basically takes the
harmonic mean of precision
and recall to just
give you one number.
So now you may wonder, why do
you need all these metrics?
So the short answer is that
sometimes you have tasks
and data sets where your
classes are very imbalanced.
So for instance, you can
have 99% of your data set
that is a positive label,
and then only 1% of the data
set which is negative.
And so here if you take
a metric like accuracy,
can be very misleading.
Because if you have a model
that would predict everything
as the majority class, then you
will have a great classifier,
but that's not the case.
So that's why precision and
recall really play a role.
So that's for the first one.
So now let's move to the
second category of NLP tasks.
So this one is the
multi-classification category.
So you have an input text and
you predict multiple things.
And we're illustrating this
with the NER task, which
as I mentioned is
about identifying
the category of given words.
And so here, for instance, we
want to identify a teddy bear
as being an entity.
I guess for that, you would use
classification metrics, but not
at the sentence level, but
more either at the token level
or at the entity-type level.
And by that I mean, let's
suppose you have a category,
let's say location.
And you want to know how
well you're predicting
words in that category.
So you would typically
aggregate these metrics
as a function of that.
Cool.
OK, let's go to the
last category, which
is, as I mentioned,
the most popular one.
So this one is
text in, text out.
So I'm illustrating this
with the machine translation
task, which is around
translating a text from a source
language to a target language.
So here you have the example
with English to French.
So cute teddy bear is reading,
un ours en peluche mignon lit.
So for that, I guess it's
harder to get data sets,
because here you need
to have pairs of texts.
So you have a very
popular data set
that's called WMT, which
stands for Workshop on Machine
Translation.
And that one contains a
bunch of paired sequences
in different languages.
So for instance, you have the
English-French, English-German,
coming from the European
Parliament data set,
for instance.
So to evaluate
those, to evaluate
the performance of your model,
it's actually a lot more tricky.
Because, as you can imagine,
you can have many different ways
to translate something.
I'm sure many of us in the
room are bilingual, trilingual.
So that's what is
making it this hard.
So in the past, people have
used several rule-based metrics
to do that.
So one that you may
have heard is BLEU.
BLEU stands for Bilingual
Evaluation Under Study.
And it is a measure of how
well your translation stands
with respect to
a reference text.
Same story for ROUGE, which is
actually a suite of metrics,
but captures that
in a different way.
And you will see that the
machine learning community
is funny, because BLEU--
I'm not sure if you know
French-- means blue,
but rouge means red.
So I guess they tried
to add some fun in this.
But the problem
with these metrics
is that you always
need a reference text.
So you basically need labels.
And in practice, having
labels is very cost expensive.
It takes a lot of time, a
lot of money to get labels.
And we will see
later in the class
that with the progress that
we have made in the LLM space,
or that the community has
made in the LLM space,
we can actually forego of
this reference-based metrics
and go towards a more
reference-free metrics.
And we will see that later on.
And then the last metric that I
will say that people sometimes
use is called perplexity.
And perplexity only looks
at the probabilities
that are output by the model.
And it basically
quantifies how surprised
the model is by its output.
So BLEU and ROUGE,
the higher the better.
Perplexity, the
lower the better.
And I guess LLMs have been
a hot topic since 2022.
But actually, the field goes
way back, way before that year.
So in the '80s, we'll
see it in a second,
but there's a class of models
that were actually thought
of, even in the '80s.
And the '90s, we had LSTMs that
we'll see also in a second.
But the problem was,
during that time,
we didn't have the internet.
We didn't have a lot of compute.
And I guess this was one of
the limiting factors which
prevented the models from
today from being trained.
And then more recently,
we've had several advances.
So Word2vec was really
one of the pioneering work
in just computing
meaningful embeddings.
And we'll see it in a second.
And then, of course, we
had the transformers,
which were part of a paper that
was published in 2017, which
is basically at the foundation
of all of the models
that you see today.
And then these models, they just
were scaled up, both by compute,
but also in terms of the data
that was used to train them.
And that's how LLMs were dubbed.
And I guess these are
more like the 2020s.
But yeah, I guess
we'll see those.
Cool.
Any questions on, I
guess, the high level?
Everyone good?
Cool.
So I guess the first
question that I
want to ask ourselves
is, what we want to do
is to have a model
that handles text.
But models, they
understand numbers,
they don't really
understand text.
So we need to somehow do
something with that text
to make it more
quantifiable, something
that a model can understand.
So if you look at a
sentence, for instance,
"a cute teddy bear is reading,"
you first need to ask yourself,
how can you cut this sentence
to pass it to a model?
So this part is
called tokenization.
And what that
entails is basically
cutting the text with respect
to some arbitrary unit of text.
So there are several
ways of doing this.
I guess the first way is doing
it completely arbitrarily.
So here, for instance,
you would have "a."
That would be one unit of text.
"Cute" could be
another unit of text.
"Teddy bear" would be
another one, and so on.
And by the way,
the unit of text is
called a token, which is why the
method is called tokenization.
Another way would be to
just separate by words.
But I guess we would have
always pros and cons.
I guess one of the goals
that we want to achieve
is for us to then be able
to represent these tokens
in a meaningful way.
So one con with doing
this at the word level
is you will end up with
words that look similar,
but that are actually
considered as different tokens.
And I guess the
limitation here is
you will need to
compute embeddings
for these similar
yet different tokens
and somehow make their
embeddings similar.
So I'll give you an example.
So let's suppose I
have the word "bear."
And then you have another
word, plural form "bears."
So these two words,
they are very similar.
Just one is singular,
the other one is plural.
If we go ahead with the
word-level tokenization,
then we will end up with
just two different entities,
which are basically just
considered as different.
Same with "run," and then
"runs," variations of verbs.
So for that reason,
people have dug
into a category
of tokenizers that
are called subword tokenizers,
which is around leveraging roots
of words in order to find what
are the common roots that we
can find in these words.
So, for instance,
for bear and bears,
you would have the bear
particle that would be shared.
And so I guess the pro is
that you get to leverage
the root of the words.
But then the con here is that
your sequence would be longer.
And we will see
why this is a con.
I guess later on, I guess
I can give you a preview.
So the complexity
of these models
is also a function of
the sequence length.
So the more tokens
you have to process,
the more time it will take
for your model to run,
because it needs to basically
process all these tokens.
So that's one con.
So pro is it leverages
the root of words.
Con is it just makes
your sequences longer.
You have a last category of
ways of tokenizing things, which
is just going at
the character level,
just like taking out characters.
So here, I guess, you and
I when we write a message,
we typically have
sometimes misspellings.
And with the subword way
of tokenizing things,
you may not be able to
recognize the word that
has been misspelled.
And this is something that
the character-level tokenizer
can, I guess, take
into consideration.
But here the problem is you
have a sequence length that's
much, much longer, which
will make your model,
I guess, take much more time
to process the sequence.
So that's one con.
And then the other
con is, I guess,
when you want to represent
each of these tokens,
I guess it's very hard to
know that a representation
of a letter really means.
Like, what does the
representation of the letter U
mean.
It's very hard.
OK, cool.
So I have just a quick recap.
So word-level is a super naive
way, super simple way of,
I guess, dividing your
text into arbitrary units.
But then the problem
is, as we mentioned,
we do not leverage
the root of words.
And I did not mention
this, but there is a term.
Whenever you cut something
and then at inference time
when you want to
make a prediction,
I guess, one prerequisite
that you have is
that you need to have the token
that you saw at training time,
you need to have it
in your training sets.
And the problem is, let's
suppose at inference time
you cut your text into words.
And let's suppose you have not
seen a word at training time.
You will need to
mark it as unknown.
And so this thing is called
OOV, Out Of Vocabulary.
So luckily, the
subword-level tokenizer
mitigates that problem.
So you have a lower risk of
OOV, but still you can have.
And as we mentioned,
in terms of the pro,
you leverage the
roots of the words.
And then character-level, it's
robust to our misspellings
and our casing errors.
But the problem is it makes
computations just much slower.
And your sequences would
be very, very long,
which will also
make your, I guess,
inference time much higher.
That sound good?
I guess this is really
the foundation, I guess,
how to handle things with text.
But yeah, does that
make sense overall?
Cool.
OK, so now what we did
is we took an input text.
What we did is we cut it into
parts that are basically tokens.
So in order for our model
to understand these tokens,
we need to find a
representation for each of them.
So here, we're going
to take a look at this.
So that's called a
word representation.
Or I guess, in a
more correct way,
it should be token
representation.
So we want to find a way to
represent each of these tokens.
So the simple and
naive way to do this
would be to just assign the
one hot vector for each word
or for each token.
So for instance,
let's suppose we have
a vocabulary of three tokens--
book, soft, and teddy bears.
We would have, let's say, soft.
That is 1, 0, 0 vector.
Teddy bear, that is, let's
say a 0, 1, 0 vector.
And book, that is, let's
say, a 0, 0, 1 vector.
So this is called a
One-Hot Encoding, OHE.
We'll typically see.
So cool.
This is a way to
represent our tokens.
But basically what
people want to do
is compare these
tokens to basically see
which ones are more
similar to what other ones.
So common similarity
measure that people use
is something called
cosine similarity.
I'm not sure if you
have heard of it.
So you can think of
it as just seeing
what angle these vectors make
in the n dimensional space.
And if, I guess, they are
pointing in the same direction,
then maybe they're similar.
Maybe if they're orthogonal,
maybe they're independent.
And if they're
completely opposite, then
maybe they're opposite.
That's basically the mental
model we want to go into.
So the problem is, if you
represent your tokens in a one
hot fashion, you will end
up with all your vectors
being orthogonal to one another.
So that's the problem.
So ideally, what we
want is for tokens
that mean the same or
similar to basically have
a high similarity.
And for tokens that are
not similar on about
different thing, to
be more orthogonal.
So here, just for illustrative
purposes, teddy bears are soft.
So you want teddy bear
and soft to be, I guess,
with a high similarity.
And let's say teddy bear and
book, which is independent,
you want them to be closer to 0.
So that's what you want.
That's what you have
with one-hot encoding,
and that's what you want.
Yeah.
Sorry?
Oh, I see.
The question is, why do
you care about the norm?
So I guess cosine similarity is
actually normalized by norms.
So it's dot products.
Oh, you mean why did I just put
dot product here instead of 2?
Oh, I see.
And your question is, why do
we not care about the norm?
Cool, I guess the viewers
know the question.
I guess these measures,
they are all measures.
They are all ways to try to
capture these similarity things.
So I guess why do you
not care about the norm?
I guess it's how people
have tried to quantify that.
I guess you will need to see
how your vectors are trained
and whether the norm would
be indicative of something.
I guess the best answer I
can give you is, I guess,
this is a measure.
This is not the perfect measure.
People may use also dot
product as a measure,
but yeah, I don't have
a great answer for you.
But as long as you
capture, I guess,
how these vectors
they're pointing,
I guess, typically what you care
about is the angle between them.
But typically, you
don't really take
into consideration the norm.
Cool, any questions?
Any other questions?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
It's a great question.
So the question is
around size of vocabulary
and how that would inform
the choice with respect
to word, subword, and how
that changes across languages.
So great question.
So I would say it
really depends, first
of all, on the tasks that
you're trying to achieve.
If your task is just
about one language,
you will just take
that same language.
You would typically go with a
subword tokenizer just because
of the reasons that
we mentioned here.
So I guess subwords is a
nice trade-off between being
able to identify
words by their roots,
like leveraging that, but also
running less into the OOV risk.
So in terms of the
size, I know that people
have tried different things.
I think typically
for English, you
would target something on the
order of tens of thousands
of vocabulary size.
But nowadays, the models,
they are multilingual,
they are also about codes.
So you will see that
the vocabulary size now
is sometimes on the order
of hundreds of thousands.
So with respect to
Chinese, so I guess
you have this difference in
characters that you're using.
So for Latin, I guess
it's the alphabet
we're all accustomed to.
But of course for
the other ones,
you'd have something
similar, but in I
guess the target
language character.
So yeah, I would say order of
magnitude, tens of thousands
for one language, hundreds of
thousands if it's multilingual.
These are the order of magnitude
that you want to target for.
Cool, yeah.
Great question.
So the question is, how do
you get those embeddings?
So it's actually the next slide.
So I'm going to talk about this.
Cool, great.
So now that we know that
the one-hot encoding is not
a good way to represent
tokens, what we want to do
is to learn those
embeddings from the data.
So I mentioned that there
was this paper that came out
in the 2010s-- so I think it was
2013-- that was called Word2vec.
And the reason why
it was so popular
is because they showed a very
intuitive and interpretable way
of seeing these embeddings,
because they were saying
something like, OK, king is to
queen, what this is to that,
like Paris is to France
what Berlin is to Germany.
So there was basically a way to
make sense of the embeddings.
So now the question is,
how did they do that?
So they had two ways of
computing these embeddings.
So one way was called
continuous bag of words.
The other one was
called skip gram.
But they all rely
on the same idea,
which is let's just leverage
texts that we have, and then try
to predict something
that is part of the text,
based on, let's
say, the context.
So for instance, continuous
bag of words, the goal
is you take into consideration
the words that are
around a given target words.
And your goal is to
predict that target word.
And skip gram is the opposite.
You go from a
target word and you
want to predict the
words that are around it.
So I guess this task is
commonly called a proxy task.
Because at the end of the
day, in this exercise,
what we care about
is not necessarily
to predict the next word,
or at least not yet.
Our goal is to learn a
representation of these words
that are meaningful.
And so here the idea is, if you
have a model that somehow knows
how to predict, let's say,
the next word, then it
means that your model has some
understanding of how language
works, which is
basically what you want.
You basically want an
embedding that is reflective
of, I guess, what language
is, which is king and queen,
or similar, Paris and
France, this is a capital.
You want to have these
associations embedded
in the representation.
And let's go through
a very simple example
of what that looks like.
So here in our example, let's
suppose that our proxy task is
about predicting the next word.
So here what we take is
a very vanilla neural
network model, which basically
receives a vector of size v,
has multiplication
and a bias term
to get a hidden state, and then
another set of multiplications
to get our final vector.
So here it's basically a
very simple neural network.
So the input is of size v.
The hidden layer is of size
d, which is typically much
smaller than the vocabulary.
So vocabulary is typically
like tens of thousands
or hundreds of thousands.
So d is typically hundred.
Like, 768, for instance, is
one example of dimension.
So it's much, much smaller.
So what we're trying to do is
to learn the word representation
through this proxy task.
And what we're
going to do is try
to consider the words as inputs
and predict the next word.
So let's go with the first
word of the sequence.
So by the way, I use token
and words interchangeably.
So let's suppose we have the
word "a," and we want to predict
the next word, which
is the word "cute."
So what we do is we take the
word "a," we take the one-hot
encoding representation, and
we pass it through the network.
So here, if you're familiar
with neural networks,
so here you have, I
guess, a multiplication
between a matrix
and this vector.
So you have a hidden
state representation,
which is a vector of size d.
So here, let's suppose it's
0.2 and 0.9, so D equal 2.
And then you have, I
guess, another pass here.
And then you get,
after softmax, a set
of probabilities
which are around
seeing what is the next word.
So in this example, we have
a vocabulary of size 6.
So the first word is
predicted with probability
0.2, second word, 0.4,
and then the other words
are all 0.1 in this example.
So let's suppose that
we want to somehow
be able to maximize
our prediction
to be the second word of the
vocabulary, which is the 0.4.
So we basically compare the
prediction with, I guess,
0, 1, 0, 0, 0, which
is the representation
of the second word
of the vocabulary.
And then we do the back
prop, we update the weights.
I'm not sure if everyone
is familiar with that part.
But the idea here is, once
you obtain a prediction,
you compute the loss, so
typically cross-entropy,
which will determine how far off
you are from the true answer.
And based on that
difference, you're
going to update the
weights in order
to make your prediction
closer to the truth.
So that's what you do.
And then you repeat
that process.
Let's suppose you take the
word "cute," which, as we said,
is the second word
in the vocabulary.
So the one-hot encoding
representation is 0, 1, 0, 0, 0.
So you go through that network,
you have a hidden state,
like the vector is 0.8 and 0.4.
You do that again.
And what you want to do is
to predict the next token,
and here is teddy bear.
And so you see now your
model in this example
is predicting the next
word to be uniform,
but you want to somehow maximize
the probability for teddy bear.
So you go about doing this again
and again for all the words.
And at the end of the
day, you obtain a model
that learns how to predict the
next word, which is basically
the proxy task.
And what you're going to do
is to take the representation
that the model learns,
which is the green units.
So what happens now is
every time you have a word,
you just represent that as a
one-hot encoding representation.
And you just multiply
this with these weights,
and then you obtain the
green representation.
And that is your
word representation.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, great question,
great question.
So the question is about
what does v correspond to
and why there's only six.
So yes, in this example we only
have six possible words, which
is basically the vocabulary
size, just like a very toy
example, because in
practice there is many more.
So I guess that's one of the
challenges with language.
So you can technically
have many variations
of words, which is why if
you take a word-level way
to divide your text into
tokens, you can end up
with the vocabulary
that's very big,
because you need to account
for all the variations of given
words.
And the other thing
that I want to point out
is, let's suppose you have
a vocabulary size of 6,
and it's the six words that
you saw at training time.
But what happens if
at inference time
you have a word that you have
not seen at training time?
And so the answer for that
is typically what people do
is they reserve a
spot for what they
call an unknown token or
out-of-vocabulary token,
which is basically you can think
of it as a bucket for everything
that we were not
able to identify.
So if let's suppose
at inference time
you have a token that you
were not able to identify,
they will all take
that representation,
which is the unknown
token representation.
And this is, by
the way, something
that I guess the word-level
tokenizer has trouble to do,
because you will have a
much bigger chance of having
out-of-vocabulary tokens.
Subword level will
have a lower chance.
And then character
level, I guess,
you don't have that problem.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah.
Cool, yeah.
Great, great question.
So first question
is, when you're done?
So the thing with the proxy task
is when you train your model,
I guess your true objective
is to not really learn--
I mean, in this case--
to learn how to
predict the next word.
Your objective is to have
meaningful representations.
But what you can do
is to somehow track
the loss function for the proxy
task that you're pursuing,
but then also taking into
consideration that this is not
necessarily your end goal.
So I guess one
very reasonable way
of going about doing this is
just to wait until your model
converges.
So here, what you do
is you track the loss
as a function of--
so there's this term "epoch,"
just how many times your model
sees the training set.
And so you compare
these different curves.
And when this converges,
this is typically a good time
to stop the training process and
just see if that makes sense.
Depends on your downstream
task, of course.
But that's one.
So your second
question-- sorry, can you
repeat the second question?
Yeah, yeah, oh, great question.
So the question is, how do you
know when the generation stops?
I guess, otherwise
it will never stop.
So yeah, exactly.
So you have some special tokens.
Typically, you have end of
sequence, end of sequence.
So typically when you have the
end of sequence token generated,
then it's when it stops.
All right.
So second question
was what informs
the size of the hidden layer?
I would say it's a
trade-off, because you
want the embedding
to be rich enough
that it can be informative
for your downstream task.
So for instance, if
you want to somehow get
an embedding of, let's
say, your sentence,
and if you want to, let's
say, do a very, very
specialized task, like with
a lot of different outcomes,
maybe you want a vector that
recaptures that, so maybe you
want a bigger vector, but if
you had a very simple task,
maybe a smaller vector
might make sense.
So I guess the size of
your hidden dimension
also impacts the complexity of
whatever you're running after.
Because of course, if
you have longer vectors,
you'll have more computation, so
your inference will be probably
more expensive, et cetera.
So I guess there's
a lot of factors.
So I guess just to recap,
one is how complicated
your downstream task is.
Second one is how
sensitive are you
with latency, cost,
all these things.
So it's really a trade-off.
But out there you
would typically
see embeddings of a pool
of hundreds or thousands.
Of course, these models,
they've been growing,
so this number may change.
But that's the
order of magnitude
that you're looking at.
Right.
This is indeed empirical.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess you can also
rely on what others found
and just go from that.
But 768, these numbers are
things that people typically
take.
Cool, yeah.
Great question.
So the question is,
how can you distinguish
words that are spelled the
same but in different contexts?
So you're way ahead of me.
So this is basically the basics.
And we're going
to tackle methods
that can tackle these problems
of just contextualizing
the word in the sentence.
So yeah, so we'll
see that in a bit.
Cool.
I'm not on time.
So I'll try to get moving.
So OK, so now what
we did was see
how we could learn
representations of tokens.
But I guess you may also
want to get representations
of sentences or pieces of text.
So one very naive way to do
that with what we saw before
is to take something like
the average of words,
let's say, the word
representations.
But the problem is you
lose a lot of meaning,
you lose the order, you lose--
and I guess here, I think
you pointed out very well,
the representations
that you learn
are token-specific, regardless
of where they're at.
So that's why we have
a class of models
that aim at capturing the
sequential nature of how
text appears.
So we're going to talk
about RNNs, which stands
for Recurrent Neural Network.
So what RNNs do is,
instead of processing words
one at a time, what
they do is they
keep a hidden representation
of the sentence so far,
and they consider
tokens one at a time.
So as I mentioned before,
this technique was actually
introduced a fair amount of
time ago, so in the '80s.
And what this model does is
it takes into consideration
the order at which words
appeared or tokens appeared.
And so in this
example, you start the,
I guess, processing at the
very beginning of the sentence.
You have some dummy hidden
states that is called A,
typically denoted
A or H. It's called
the hidden state, activation, or
even sometimes a context vector.
And you have some
kind of a module that
takes into account the
hidden state so far
and the word at time step
t, so here time step 1.
So here what it does is it takes
in the meaning of the sentence
so far and takes
into consideration
the word that is happening now.
And it produces an
output vector that
here can be used to try
to predict the next word.
So for instance here we
have this hidden state
and the representation
of the word
that then you have some
matrix multiplications
in this blue box.
And you have an
output vector that you
try to train on
predicting the next words.
And then you keep on
doing that by keeping
track of these hidden states.
And so you repeat the process.
And I guess the way you would
interpret these hidden states
is it's a representation of
the sequence process so far.
So the good thing with RNNs
is now the word order matters.
And you're also able
to encode the sentence
in a more natural way.
So let's see roughly
how it works.
So we have the same
favorite example,
so cute teddy bear is reading.
So you would have the token
A. You want one-hot encoding
vector.
You pass it through
your network.
You compute the hidden state.
You try to predict cute.
But then you keep track
of the hidden state.
And then you input that
into another module.
And then you also
consider the next words.
So you consider not only the
word itself, but also the hidden
state of this sentence so far.
And you try to predict the next
word again, and again and again.
So this is RNN.
So RNNs were used
for a bunch of tasks,
and just like mapping that
back to the categories
that we saw before.
For classification
purposes, you can basically
use the hidden state of the
last word in your sentence.
For instance, if
you want to predict
like the sentiment
of a review, you
would take basically
the last vector here
and try to project
it into the space
of the predictions or the labels
that you want to predict on.
So for instance, if you
want positive or negative,
you basically project that
vector onto that space.
You can do that here.
For multi-classification,
so you would basically
have the representation
of the token of interest,
and you would project that.
Or for generation,
you would basically
process the whole
source text, and then
have a context vector, a.k.a.
activation vector, a.k.a.
hidden state at the
end of your processing,
which will then be used to
decode the output prediction.
So this is how you would use
an RNN for each of these tasks.
So the reason why you have not
really heard of RNNs these days
is because they had some
pros, but a lot of cons.
So one of the cons is that
the meaning of the sentence
is basically solely encapsulated
into this hidden state.
So you have this problem
of long-range dependencies,
which basically impacts your
ability to quote, unquote,
"remember" what the
model saw in the past,
which is why you have another
class of models that try
to build on RNNs.
So this one is called LSTMs,
Long Short-Term Memory.
And the goal of that extension
is to have the way to somehow
keep track of the things that
are quote, unquote, "important"
to remember, on top of the
hidden state that we talked
about.
So here you have a of t,
which is your activation,
basically the sequence
so far encoded in there.
And then you have
another quantity
that you track that is
called the cell state.
It's denoted c here.
So this architecture aims
at improving that piece,
but I guess it was
not perfect either.
But yeah, so that
was the main issue
of RNN-based methods,
which is that they
have this issue of forgetting
what was in the past.
So you will see
in the literature
that this phenomenon is
called vanishing gradient.
And the reason why it's called
that way-- so I know we're
running out of time, but I'm
going to just explain that part.
So in order for you to predict,
let's say, the last words,
you're basically dependent
on every hidden state
that came before that.
So far so good?
And so whenever you want to
update the weights of your model
to match the prediction here
with the actual prediction, when
you do the back
propagation, you somehow
need to take into account that
the value here is basically
not only a matter
of this computation,
but also this computation
or this computation
that basically happened
in a sequential manner.
So you have this phenomenon
of trying to, I guess,
back-propagate through time.
But the problem is,
in practice when
you write that down-- so
it's a very ugly formula.
But when you write
that down, it ends up
being a product of a
bunch of quantities
that can-- so if it's greater
than 1, then it's exploding.
If it's less than
1, it's vanishing.
Because if you multiply a lot
of things that are less than 1,
it just goes to 0.
So I guess if you have
something that you're
trying to update that
goes to 0, basically
you have trouble just
doing your updates.
So that's a
high-level intuition.
This is not the
focus of this class,
which is why I'm not
going into the detail
of this ugly formulas.
But I hope you get the idea
that for remembering things
from the past, it's
not doing a great job,
because of this sequential,
I guess, characteristic.
Does that make sense?
OK, I hope the next thing
will make a bit more sense.
But before that, I'll
just recap what we saw.
So our goal is to
represent text.
So we first started
with representing
words or tokens, which was what
we tried to do with Word2vec.
And we saw that it was a good
way to leverage proxy tasks
to learn this representation.
But we had a bunch
of limitations.
And one of them
that you mentioned
was that this was not
aware of the context.
And also the word
order didn't count.
And so you have this
other class of methods
that is able to take into
consideration the words,
but then they have some
trouble keeping track of things
when the sequence
gets very long.
And you have this problem
of vanishing gradients
or long-range dependencies.
So whenever you
see this term, it's
basically referring to that.
And also another thing
that I have not mentioned,
but the computations
are very slow.
So when you want to train
these models, at training time,
in order to predict
this word, you basically
need to compute all these
hidden states before.
So when your sequence
gets very long,
it just takes a very long time.
So for all of these reasons,
for I guess what reason.
So for the fact that the model
has trouble remembering things
from the past, people have tried
having more direct connections
between something and
the thing from the past,
and this is the idea
behind attention.
So what attention
does is it tries
to have a direct link between
what we're trying to predict
and something from the past.
So in this example,
let's suppose
I'm trying to translate
an English sentence
into a French one.
So here I guess the
input sentence is given.
I'm computing the hidden state.
I'm processing
words one at a time.
This is my traditional RNN.
So "a cute teddy
bear is reading."
So here I have a hidden
state that I'm then decoding.
And you can imagine
that when wanting
to generate the next
word of my translation,
it would be great if I knew
what word I'm trying to predict.
Or in other words,
it would be great
if I could take a peek at a
certain area of the input text.
So the idea behind
attention is to have
a direct link between what
you're trying to predict
and things before.
This is the idea
behind attention.
And so it was
introduced in 2014.
And yeah, again, this
is trying to solve
for these long-range
dependency issues.
And so yeah, this example
we want to do that.
And this concept is going to
actually be key for this class.
Because we're going to see
that the attention mechanism is
the thing that is going
to make everything--
I mean, most of the things work.
And this is actually
the main principle
that the transformer
paper relies on.
So the transformer, which
is the core architecture
that we will see in this
class, has been introduced
or was introduced in
2017 in this paper named
Attention is All You Need.
So even from the title, you
can see that the authors wanted
to just rely on that part.
So what the authors
tried to do was
to move away from this
sequential way of processing
the text, and instead
let the model just
have direct connections with
all parts of the text at once.
So that is called
self-attention.
So they tried that
on translation tasks.
And they just realized that
it was giving great results.
So back to the example
that we're still using,
a cute teddy bear is reading
Here what we would say
is that in order to
compute the representation
of the token teddy
bear, we're going
to look at all the other
tokens in the sequence at once,
and directly with direct links.
So I guess back to
your question-- here,
we would have a
representation of teddy bear
that would be unique to the
context that it is part of.
So back to your question about
riverbank and robbing a bank,
like here the bank would have
different representations.
So this is the idea.
I guess, does the idea
roughly make sense?
And again, this is called
the self-attention mechanism.
Afshine, how am I doing on time?
8.
I have 8?
OK, cool.
OK, so this is the idea.
So now I'm going
to just introduce
another set of ideas
which is more terminology
but is going to
be very important.
So when you want to express
something in terms of something
else, we use the words "query,"
"key," and "value," Q, K and V.
So in this example, our
goal is to figure out
what other tokens is the query
teddy bear more similar to.
So here the question
is, OK, you have a query
and you want to see what
other tokens are most similar.
And so what you're
going to do is
to look at all the other
tokens which are basically
composed of keys and values.
So we're going to compare
the query to the key
to quantify how similar your
query is to a given key,
and take the
corresponding value.
So we'll see that
in this example,
so let's suppose you want to
express teddy bear in terms
of everything else.
What you're going
to do is you're
going to take the
query teddy bear,
and you're going to compare that
query with all the other keys
to see which element
is most similar,
and then weight the
more similar ones
and take their associated value.
So that's a very high level
idea of how these things are.
Of course, we're going to
see exactly how they work.
But that's the general idea.
OK, cool.
And speaking of query
and key and value,
we will also see that one
benefit of expressing things
this way is that we
can express doing
this self-attention computation
across the whole sequence
in a matrix format.
And GPUs love matrices.
So it's really made for
the hardware that we have.
And I guess what
I mentioned here
can be expressed in
a form of softmax
of the query and the key,
which is basically a way
to get some kinds of
weights of which values
will be more important.
So for instance, if a
value is more important,
you have bigger weight.
And another one will
be less important,
you'll have a smaller weight.
And you basically multiply
that by the value.
So don't worry, we'll have
a detailed example after.
So if it still feels very
high-level fuzzy, don't worry.
We'll have a
detailed walkthrough.
And yes, so this
is how it works.
OK, cool.
Any questions on what
self-attention is?
Yeah.
Great, great question.
So the question is, what
is value, what is key?
I guess, how to get those?
What do they mean?
So first of all, I just want
to say that these quantities,
they are learned.
So you are not fixing them.
But from an
interpretation standpoint,
you can interpret
that the key is there
for you to figure out which one
is most similar to the query.
And the value is
the actual value
that is associated
with that element.
So here, you will have
something like you
want to express this in
terms of all the values.
So the weights in
your weighted average
will be basically the
dot product between--
basically-- between
the query and the key.
And the value will be the
actual vector that you will use.
But again, these
things are learned.
And something I
have not mentioned,
but you mentioned it
correctly, so we're
going to actually do projections
to obtain these quantities.
And these projections are
actually learned by the model.
That's good?
OK, cool.
So with that, we have
15 minutes, right,
to talk about the architecture.
OK, so at a very
high level, in order
to make the self-attention
mechanism happen,
the authors propose
an architecture
that is composed of two
parts, an encoder, which
is on the left
side, and a decoder,
which is on the right side.
So the application that
they have is translation.
So what will go
through the encoder
is the input text in
your source language.
And what is going to
go through the decoder
is the target language
that you're predicting.
So the high-level
idea is you're going
to compute meaningful
embeddings from your input text
by passing them
through the encoder.
And you want that self-attention
mechanism to apply,
meaning you want to compute
representations of each token
as a function of others.
And you do that by using a layer
called the attention layer.
So multi-head attention
layer, but multi-head
is just doing this
computation in different ways
to just allow the model to
learn different representations
or different projections.
But the idea here is you are
going to input your input text,
and all the tokens
in your input text
are going to attend
to one another.
So for instance, a cute
teddy bear is reading,
you are going to compute
the representation
of all the tokens in
this text basically
as a function of others.
And you're going to do that
with the encoder, so here
with the multi-head attention.
And then you have a
feedforward layer,
which is just to
let the model learn
another kind of projection.
And what you're going
to obtain at the end
of your encoding process
is rich representations
of the tokens from
the input sentence.
So far, so good?
But now your goal is to actually
translate the input sentence.
So what you're going to do
is to start your translation
with, let's suppose, the
beginning of sentence token,
so your first token.
And what you're going to do
is use all the representations
from your input
sentence in order
to figure out what
to predict next.
So this what I just said is
the cross-attention layer,
which is the one that is
the second, so this one,
which basically--
I'm not sure if
you see the arrows,
but there are two arrows
coming from the encoder, one
arrow coming from the decoder.
Can anyone tell me what
the arrow from the decoder
represents?
Is decoder a query key or value?
I guess there is 1
over 3, 33% chance.
Who wants to try?
Is it key?
OK.
Query?
So the way to think
about it is you're
trying to ask yourself, what are
the words from the input that
matter.
Right?
So basically, you
want know, given
your query, what are the
elements from the inputs that
matter?
So here, this arrow
is indeed the query,
because this is the thing
that you want to figure out.
And the keys and
values are actually
coming from the encoder,
which are basically
coming from the input sequence.
And then you have
another attention layer,
which is this one.
And that one is
trying to figure out
what other tokens of the output
sentence that you're decoding
is going to be useful to
predict the next token.
So let's suppose
you start decoding
and you say, un ours en
peluche, which is in French.
To predict the next word, you
want to basically figure out
what are the tokens
translated so far that
are going to be useful
to predict the next word.
So this is what this
attention layer is about.
And it's called
masked, because it only
looks at the tokens
that translated so far.
It does not look at
tokens that were not
translated, because of course
they were not translated.
So there's no way, like on
the right side of the token
that you're trying to predict.
Cool.
So at a very high level, you
have this attention layer,
which is present in the encoder,
which is present in the decoder,
but it has several,
I guess, use cases.
So the attention layer here
aims at computing embeddings
from the input sentence as
a function of themselves.
And then the ones
from the decoder,
so the first one, the
masked self-attention layer,
aims at expressing something as
a function of everything that
has been decoded so far.
And the second one, the
cross-attention layer,
tries to express things
as a function of what
has been seen in the input.
So here, given
that you are having
direct links to
different tokens,
you don't have this
sense of order.
Because in the RNN,
you are basically
expressing things one at a time.
So you had some sense
of the word order,
but here you don't
have it, because it's
like a direct link, which
is why you have position
encodings, which
are there to inform
on the position of the
word in the sequence.
So we're not going to
dig into that today,
but I just want
to call that out.
So at a very high
level, and we're
going to see this in the
detailed example, what
we do is in order to translate
a sentence from source language
to target language,
we're first going
to tokenize the text, so
dividing into arbitrary units.
We're going to learn an
embedding for these tokens.
So this is what the
input embedding is about.
Then we're going to add
some encoding with respect
to the position.
We're not going to talk about
it today, but just good to note.
And then we go
through the encoder.
So the encoder
tries to figure out
how to express things as
a function of other things
from the inputs.
So it does that in the
multi-head attention layer.
And then it goes through a
feedforward neural network,
which is just a way to just
project the vectors to just
have some more degrees of
freedom to learn things.
And then once you have these
representations from the input,
you're then going to
start your translation.
So you start with the BOS token.
And what you're
trying to do is figure
out what the next word is.
So you're going to
see, OK, what are
the words that were
translated so far that
are useful for translation.
So this is what the masked
multi-head attention layer does.
And then you have
another attention layer,
which is about expressing
things as a function of what
was in the input, which is
the cross-attention layer
over there.
And then you have a feedforward
neural network to, again,
give some more
degrees of freedom.
And at the end of the day, you
have a vector that you then
go through softmax.
And it just is a way for you
to guess what is the next word.
So you have a vector
of vocabulary size.
And you're going to use
these values to determine
what is your next word.
Easy, right?
Any questions on this?
Yeah.
All right, that's
a great question.
The question is,
what does head mean?
So I guess I went too fast.
I ignored that part.
But when you do the
self-attention computation,
you basically make queries
interact with keys,
and then take the
corresponding value.
But nothing prevents you from
doing that several times.
So the term "head" is given to
the projection matrices that you
use to obtain the
query, key, and value.
And when you have several
heads, what you're doing
is you're allowing your model
to learn different projections.
So it's basically
an additional degree
of freedom for your model to
learn different associations
between your vectors.
So it's a great question.
So typically it will be noted
lowercase h, number of heads.
And this is what
this corresponds to.
Does that answer your question?
Cool, very cool.
OK, we have a lot to
discuss, but here I
had the slide actually for this.
So this is the multi-heads
that you were mentioning.
So we're basically running
the self-attention computation
several times in
parallel, again,
with different projection
matrices that the model learns.
So in case you have a
computer vision background,
it is similar to having multiple
filters in your convolution.
So it's the same idea,
but it's different here.
Yeah, great question.
So the question is, are
the projections different?
So we're typically not
constraining things.
We're just letting
the model learn.
But in practice, it just
tends to learn different ways
of saying the same thing.
So yeah, typically
there is no constraint.
Of course, you have papers
that dig into how about
if you change this.
But typically you don't
have any constraint.
Cool, great.
OK, I will just
mention one trick,
another trick that the
transformer authors use.
So it's called label smoothing.
Who has heard of
label smoothing?
So one new thing
here is in NLP when
you want to predict
what comes next,
there's typically
more than one way.
When you say, what
a great day, what
a great lecture, what a
great book, what a great--
there's always multiple choices.
There's more than one
way of filling that gap.
So label smoothing
is a technique
that tries to
intuitively address that.
And what it does is, instead of
saying predict this word 100%
is this one, there is no other
words, what it does is it says,
predict this word, but there's
a chance it's not this word.
And in practice, what it does is
it takes the one-hot encoding.
And instead of saying
it's a 1, 0, 0, 0,
that you need to predict,
it says it's actually
1 minus epsilon, and then
epsilon over v minus 1, I guess,
is you're trying to predict.
So in practice,
it's a method that
tends to make your
model be more unsure.
Again, to be less sure
about this prediction
because you always tell it,
OK, try to predict this,
but actually it's possible
it's not the correct value.
But in practice, the
authors see that it
tends to improve
metrics like BLEU,
which is a proxy metric
for translation tasks.
So yeah, I think this method
is pretty general for NLP.
So yeah, it's a
good one to know.
And with that, I think there's
about 20-ish minutes left.
So yeah, Shervine
is going to walk you
through an end-to-end example.
And with that, you--
yeah, Oh, u?
So I guess here you can think of
this as, I guess, some quantity.
It's not defined,
so some quantity.
And the delta is like one
hot, if you want, something
like this.
It can also be a constant.
Yeah, yeah.
So question is, is
there a relation
with explore and exploit?
It's an interesting one.
So why would softmax give
it for free, by the way?
Right, but I guess
it would still--
so I guess at the end
of the day, what you're
trying to do is to compare
your prediction with respect
to the label.
So I guess the question
here is, do you
want to compare with
1, 0, 0, 0, or do you
want to compare with something
that is not 1, 0, 0, 0.
So I guess softmax does
not allow you to do that.
Exactly, yes.
So I'm not sure if
this was super clear,
but this is actually the label.
So what you're trying to
predict is not 1, 0, 0.
But we change the label in
a way that makes the model,
I guess, predict something
that is less sure, I guess.
Cool, thanks.
And with that, yeah, Shervine.
OK, great.
Thank you, Afshine.
And yes, so we saw basically
how the transformer worked.
And now we're going to
piece it all together
with the one specific example.
OK, great.
So let's take our
favorite example again.
So a cute teddy bear is reading.
And then we'll go all
together through each step.
So first we start
with tokenization.
So as we said, we can use
any arbitrary decomposition
to decompose this into tokens.
And then as someone
mentioned, you
need to have some way to
indicate the start and the end
of a sequence.
So typically, this is done
with the BOS and EOS tokens.
So you add them.
So now let's focus
on the composition
of each token representation.
So you have its embedding.
That is learned.
And as Afshine
mentioned, in order
to have an idea of what is
the position of the words
or the token, I should say
as part of the sequence,
you have some added
information that
is in the form of a
position embedding.
And here, the original
paper uses the convention
of some sines and cosines
that it adds additively
to the representation.
So it's like an
element-wise addition.
OK, great.
So now you have a position-aware
embedding for your token.
And you repeat that for
each of your tokens.
So now you can see all
of these embeddings
in the format of a matrix,
which is of size d model, which
is the size of your embeddings.
And then the other
dimension is the length
of the sequence, so typically n.
So all make sense so far?
Any questions on the inputs?
OK, great.
So now we will send
this representation
through the encoder.
So as Afshine said, you have
this concept of self-attention.
And the way you
perform self-attention
is that you take this input
and project it on three spaces.
So you project it to the
space Wq, you get queries.
You project the same embeddings
in the space Wk, you get keys.
And you do the same for
values, you get your values.
And then Wq, Wk, and Wv
are learned by the model.
They are basically
projection matrices.
So far, so good?
So now with all of
that in mind, you
can apply the formula
that Afshine mentioned,
that is the
self-attention formula,
which is softmax of Qk
transpose over square root of dk
times v, which gives you another
matrix out of all of this.
Now let's pause for
a second and look
at how this computation
is done in practice
and what every step means.
So let's look at Q.
When you compute Q,
basically you project your
embeddings into that space.
What do you obtain?
You obtain a matrix where each
row represents a given query.
When you say k
transpose, it's basically
the same matrix, but
transposed, where
each column represents the key
representation of each token.
Now let's mix them together
with the matrix multiplication.
So when you multiply
each of them,
you see that each row
represents the projection
of the query over each key, such
that when you take the matrix
multiplication and get the
softmax of all of this,
you get a probability
distribution
of the projection of the query
over keys for each query.
Each line will have this.
And I don't know if anyone asked
the question regarding why do we
scale by square root of dk?
So it could be dq as well
because matrix multiplication,
like the dot product
here, enforces
the fact that dq equals dk.
And basically, what you see
is that these dot products has
the dimension of key
and queries grows,
it will tend to grow as well.
So you want to normalize
these dot products.
And this is why you
divide by square root
of the dimension of keys.
OK, great.
And then now you have your
softmax of all of these,
and then you multiply
it with the matrix
v. And this is Afshine explained
as having the query projected
on the space of keys,
and then multiplied
by the corresponding value.
So the value is
the representation
of the corresponding
key that we project on.
So you end up with a weighted
sum of values for each query.
OK, great.
Does that make sense so far?
OK, awesome.
And someone asked, what
is the multi-head stuff?
So you're right, it's not
just single one, one time
that it's done.
It's actually done each times.
And what you obtain is, like,
all of that is done in parallel.
And at the end, you
obtain h such matrices.
And you concatenate them
with respect to the columns.
And at the end of this, you
have another projection matrix
that you call Wo that will
project all of these back
to the original
dimension of embeddings.
So it's a way for the
network to basically have
a dimension-invariant way--
bless you-- to go from
the original dimension
back to the original one.
Any questions?
Yep.
So the question is regarding h.
Is it possible to get the
same result each time?
And if so, concatenate the
same thing, will it be helpful?
Did I get the question right?
So what makes it different?
So it's the magic
of gradient descent.
So the network has an
objective function at the end.
It has degrees of freedom.
Its incentive is to build a
representation that will be
helpful to learn the next word.
So it doesn't have an incentive
to copy the same thing
or do the same mechanism.
And this is why in practice
you see the model converge
towards building different
representations that it can then
concatenate and then project
into something useful.
So what makes it such that
you don't have the same thing?
Nothing.
Like, you don't have
any constraints.
But the nature of the learning
that you let the model have
makes it do so in practice.
Any other questions?
And that is a great question.
I mean, typically gradient
descent does wonders.
OK great.
So now that we have gone through
the self-attention layer,
you have another
component that is the FFN.
And I think there was a
question just here regarding
how to choose the dimension
of the hidden layer
with respect to the
input and outputs.
So when Afshine
mentioned Word2vec,
typically you have
a smaller dimension
than the input and output.
But here, actually,
the hidden layer
is of a bigger dimension
than input and output.
And the rationale
for that is that you
want to have enough degrees of
freedom for the model to learn
useful representations.
So it's a way to complexify
the features that you learn.
And, yeah [INAUDIBLE].
OK, great.
And you don't have just
one encoder module.
You have actually n of them,
big N in the original paper.
And at the end of
all of this, you
have an encoded context-aware
set of embeddings.
And then each of
these setups encoded
embeddings will be those that
will be fed to the n decoders.
So you have like a stacked
succession of n encoders.
You have a stacked
succession of n decoders.
And the last representation
of the encoder
is what you will feed to the
cross-attention of each decoder.
So yeah, we're going to
see that more in detail.
So how do we even start
the decoding process?
So you start with the BOS token.
Basically saying to
the model, hey, we
need to predict the
next word, let's start.
So what happens to the BOS
token at the very beginning?
So you feed it to the decoder.
And then similarly as
before for the encoder,
you have a self-attention layer.
And as Afshine mentioned, the
self-attention layer is causal.
So the attention will be
done on the same token
and the tokens that precede it.
So on this first BOS token,
you don't see a difference,
because it will just
attend to itself.
But when you have other tokens
that you want to decode,
you will have this
difference in where you
attend with respect to decoder.
OK, great, goes through
the self-attention layer.
And then you have
what I mentioned
to be the cross-attention
that takes as keys and values
these encoded
embeddings as inputs.
And then the queries
are those that come out
of the self-attention layer.
OK, great.
And then once you do
this cross-attention,
you have, just like
in the encoder,
an FFN component that makes
the representation richer.
Was there a question there?
No.
And then at the very end, so
you do all of that n times.
And at the very end of
the decoding process,
you have a linear projection
and a softmax layer
to turn the prediction
of the next word
into a probability distribution
over the vocabulary.
OK, great.
So we saw how to do that
for the next word here.
And basically you do
that again and again.
So you have found
your next token,
which is like a
one-hot basically
encoding of what you want.
And then you take that
embedding and then put it back
in the decoder and
continue this process.
And when do you stop?
It's a question for you all.
When you hit the EOS token.
Yeah, yeah exactly.
OK, great.
And with this process,
it's basically
how the authors of this
original landmark paper
did machine translation.
So this is typically the
use case that was presented.
Any questions?
OK, awesome.
And with that, thank
you for your attention.
[APPLAUSE]